[Music]
Reedman
reads The giver by Lois Lowry narrated by Fraser
[Music]
Reedman chapter 1 It was all almost December, and Jonas was beginning to be
frightened. No. Wrong word, Jonas thought frighten meant that deep, sickening
feeling of something terrible about to happen. Frightened was the way he had
felt a year ago when an unidentified aircraft had overflown the community
twice he'd seen it both times. Squinting toward the sky he'd seen the sleek jet,
almost a blur at its high speed, go past, and a second later he heard the
blast of the sound of followed. Then one more time, a moment
later, from the opposite direction, the same plane that first he'd been only
fascinated. He' never seen aircraft so close, for it was against the rules for
Pilots to fly over the community. Occasionally, when supplies
were delivered by cargo planes to the landing field across the
river, the children rolled their bikes to the riverbank and watched, intrigued, the
unloading and then the takeoff directed to the west, always away from the
community. But the aircraft a year ago that had been different. It was not a
squat fat bellied cargo plane but a needle-nosed single pilot
jet. Jonas, looking around anxiously, had seen others— —adults as well as children
sto what they were doing and wait, confused, for an explanation of the frightening
event. Then all of the citizens had been ordered to go into the nearest building
and stay there. IMMEDIATELY, the rasping voice through the speakers had
said, LEAVE YOUR BICYCLES WHERE THEY ARE. Instantly, obediently, Jonas had
dropped his bike on its side on the path behind his family's dwelling. He had run
indoors and stayed there, alone. His parents were both at work, and
his little sister, Lily, was at the child care Center where she spent her after
school hours. Looking through the front window, he had seen no people: none of the
busy afternoon crew of the Street cleaner Landscape Workers, and Food
Delivery people who usually populated the community at that time of day. He saw
only the abandoned bikes here and there on their sides; an upturned wheel on one
was still revolving slowly. He had been frightened then. The sense of his own community silent,
waiting, had made his stomach churn. He had trembled. But it had been nothing. Within
minutes the speakers had crackled again, and the voice, reassuring now and less
urgent, had explained that a pilot in training had misread his navigational
instructions and made a wrong turn. Desperately the Pilot had been
trying to make his way back before his error was noticed. NEEDLESS TO SAY, HE WILL BE
RELEASED, the voice had said, followed by silence. There was an ironic tone to that
final message, as if the Speaker found it amusing; and Jonas had smiled a little,
though he knew what a grim statement it had been. For a contributing citizen to
be released from the community was a final decision, a terrible punishment, an
overwhelming statement of failure. Even the children were scolded
if they used the term lightly at play, jeering at a teammate who missed a catch
or stumbled in a race. Jonas had done it once shouted at his best friend, "That's
it, Asher! You're getting released!" when Asher's clumsy air had lost a match for his
team. He had been taken aside for a brief and serious talk by the coach, had hung
his head with guilt and embarrassment, and apologized to Asher after the
game. Now, thinking about the feeling of fear as he pedal home along the river
path, he remembered that moment of palpable stomach sinking terror when the
aircraft had streaked above. It was not what he was feeling now
with December approaching. He searched for the right word to describe his own
feeling. Jonas was careful about language. Not like his friend, Asher, who
talk too fast and mix things up, scrambling words and phrases until they
were barely recognizable and often very funny. Jonas grinned, remembering the
morning that Asher had dashed into the classroom, late as usual, arriving
breathlessly in the middle of the chanting of the morning anthem. When the
class took their seats at the conclusion of the patriotic hym
Asher remained standing to make his public apology as was
required. "I apologize for inconveniencing my learning community." Asher ran through
the standard apology phrase rapidly, still catching his breath. The Instructor in class waited
patiently for his explanation. The students had all been grinning, because
they had listened to Asher's explanation so many times before. "I left home at the correct time
but when I was riding along near the hatchery, the crew was separating some
salmon. I guess I just got distraught, watching them. "I apologized to my classmates," Asher
concluded. He smoothed his rumpled tunic and sat down. "We accept your apology as The class
recited the standard response in unison. Many of the students were biting
their lips to keep from laughing. "I accept your apology, Asher," the
Instructor said. He was smiling. "And I thank you, because once again you have
provided an opportunity for a lesson in language. 'Distraught' is too strong an
adjective to describe salmon viewing He turned and wrote "distraught" on the
instructional board. Beside it he wrote "distracted." Jonas, nearing his home now, smiled at the
recollection. Thinking, still, as he wheeled his bike into its narrow port
beside the door, he realized that frightened was the wrong word to
describe his feelings, now that December was almost here. It was too strong an
adjective. He had waited long time for this special December. Now that it was almost upon him,
he wasn't frightened, but he was eager, he decided. He was eager for it to
come. And he was excited, certainly. All of the Els were excited
about the event that would be coming so soon. But there was a little shutter of
nervousness when he thought about it, about what might
happen. Apprehensive, Jonas decided. That's what I
am. "Who wants to be the first tonight, for feelings?" Jonas's father asked, at the
conclusion of their evening meal. It was one of the rituals, the evening telling of
feelings. Sometimes Jonas and his sister, Lily, argued over turns, over who would
get to go first. Their parents, of course, were part of the the ritual; they, too,
told their feelings each evening. But like all parents— —all adults— —they didn't
fight and Weedle for their turn. Nor did Jonas, tonight. His feelings were too
complicated this evening. He wanted to share them, but he wasn't eager to begin
the process of sifting through his own complicated emotions, even with the help
that he knew his parents could give. "You go, Lily," he said, seeing his
sister, who was much younger— —only a Seven— —wiggling with impatience in her
chair. "I felt very angry this afternoon," Lily announced. "My child care group was
at the play area, and we had a visiting group of sants and they didn't obey the
rules at all. One of them— —a male; I don't know his name— —kept going right to the
front of the line for the slide, even though the rest of us were all waiting. I
felt so angry at him. I made my hand into
a fist, like this." She held up a clenched fist and the rest of the family smiled
at her small defiant gesture. "Why do you think the visitors didn't obey the rules?" Mother
asked. Lily considered, and shook her head.
"I don't know. They acted like like..." "Animals Jonah suggested. He
laughed. "That's right," Lily said, laughing too. "Like
animals." Neither child knew what the word meant, exactly, but it was often used to
describe someone uneducated or clumsy, someone who didn't fit
in. "Where were the visitors from?" Father asked. Lily frowned, trying to
remember. "Our leader told us, when he made the welcome speech, but I can't
remember. I guess I wasn't paying attention. It was from another community.
They had to leave very early, and they had their midday meal on the
bus." Mother nodded. "Do you think it's possible that their rules may be
different? And so they simply don't know what your play area rules were?" Lily shrugged, and
nodded. "I suppose." "You've visited other communities,
haven't you?" Jonas asked. "My group has, often." Lily nodded again. "When we were
Sixes, we went and shared a whole school day with a group of Sixes in their
community." "How did you feel when you were there?" Lily frowned. "I felt strange. Because their
methods were different. They were learning usages that my group hadn't learned yet, so we felt
stupid." Father was listening with interest. "I'm thinking, Lily," he said, "about
the boy who didn't obey the rules today.
Do you think it's possible that he felt strange and stupid, being in a new place
with rules that he didn't know about?" Lily pondered that. "Yes," she said,
finally. "I feel a little sorry for him," Jonas said, "even though I don't know him.
I feel sorry for anyone who is in a place where he feels strange and
stupid." "How do you feel now, Lily?" Father asked. "Still angry?" "I guess not," Lily decided.
"I guess I feel a little sorry for him.
And sorry I made a fist." She grinned. Jonas smiled back at his sister.
Lily's feelings were always straightforward, fairly simple, usually
easy to resolve. He guessed that his own had been, too, when he was a
Seven. He listened politely, though not very attentively, while his father took
his turn, describing a feeling of worry that he'd had that day at work: a concern
about one of the new children who wasn't doing well. Jonas's father's title was Nurturer.
He and the other Nurturers were responsible for all the physical and
emotional needs of every new child during its earliest life. It was a very
important job, Jonas knew, but it wasn't one that interested him much. "What gender
is it?" Lily asked. "Male," Father said. "He's a sweet little male with a lovely
disposition. But he isn't growing as fast as he should should and he doesn't sleep
soundly. We have him in the extra care section for supplementary nurturing the
committee is beginning to talk about releasing him." "Oh, no, Mother murmured
sympathetically. "I know how sad that must make you feel." Jonas and Lily both nodded
sympathetically as well. Release of new children was always sad, because they
hadn't had a chance to enjoy life within the community yet. And they hadn't done anything
wrong. There were only two occasions of release which were not punishment.
Release of the elderly, which was a time of celebration for a life well and fully
lived; and release of a new child which always brought a sense of what could we have
done This was especially troubling for the Nurturers, like Father, who felt they
had failed somehow. But it happened very rarely. "Well," Father said, "I'm going to
keep trying. I may ask the committee for permission to bring him here at night, if
you don't mind. You know what the night crew Nurturers are like. I think this
little guy needs something extra." "Of course," Mother said, and Jonas
and Lily nodded. They had heard Father complain about the night crew before. It
was a lesser job night crew nurturing a sign to those who lack the interest or
skills or insight for the more vital jobs of the daytime
hours. Most of the people on the night crew had not even been given spouses
because they lacked, somehow, the essential capacity to connect to others,
which was required for the creation of a family unit. "Maybe we could even keep him," Lily
suggested sweetly, trying to look innocent. The look was fake, Jonas knew;
they all knew. "Lily," Mother reminded her, smiling, "you know the
rules." Two children— —one male, one female— —to each family unit. It was written very
clearly in the rules. Lily giggled. "Well," she said, "I thought maybe just this
once." Next, Mother, who held a prominent position at the Department of Justice,
talked about her feelings. Today a repeat offender had been brought before her, someone who had
broken the rules before. Someone who she hoped had been adequately and fairly punished, and who
had been restored to his place: to his job, his home, his family
unit. To see him brought before her a second time caused her overwhelming
feelings of frustration and anger. And even guilt, that she hadn't made a
difference in his life. "I feel frightened, too, for him," she
confessed. "You know that there's no third chance. The rules say that if there's a
third transgression, he simply has to be released." Jonas shivered. He knew it
happened. There was even a boy in his group of Els whose father had been
released years before. No one ever mentioned it; the disgrace was
unspeakable. It was hard to imagine.
Lily stood up and went to her mother. She stroked her mother's
arm. From his place at the table, Father reached over and took her hand. Jonas reached for the
other. One by one, they comforted her. Soon she smiled, thanked them, and murmured that she felt
soothed. The ritual continued. "Jonas?" Father asked. "You're last, tonight." Jonas
sighed. This evening he almost w have preferred to keep his feelings hidden.
But it was, of course, against the rules. "I'm feeling apprehensive," he
confessed, glad that the appropriate descriptive word had finally come to
him. "Why is that, son?" His father looked concerned. "I know there's really nothing
to worry about," Jonas explained, "and that every adult has been through it. I know
you have, Father, and you too, Mother. But it's the Ceremony that I'm apprehensive
about. It's almost December." Lily looked up, her eyes wide.
"The Ceremony of 12 she whispered in an aw voice. Even the smallest children— —Lily's
age and younger— —knew that it lay in the future for each of them. "I'm glad you
told us of your feelings," Father said. "Lily," Mother said, beckoning to the
little girl, "Go on now and get into your night clothes Father and I are going to
stay stay here and talk to Jonas for a while." Lily sighed, but obediently she got
down from her chair. "Privately?" she asked.
Mother nodded. "Yes," she said, "this talk will be a private one with Jonas
[Music]